Empresses in the Palace—the Legend of Zhen Huan
Adapted from the novel by Liu Lian Zi
Translators: The Magpie Bridge Brigade 鹊桥小队翻译组
https://magpiebridgebrigade.cn
Twitter/FB/IG @BrigadeMagpie 公众号/微博: 鹊桥小队翻译组
Theme: Unfortunate Love
I can cut a thousand strands of hair
but I cannot sever the tangled threads of my mind.
Bowing with my hands clasped, I give away my throne.
Lowering my head, devoted to the beauty by my side.
The wheel of fate turns, granting blessings or misfortune.
Will it be destiny’s trial or reward?
Heaven’s will cannot be known,
weaving together weals and woes.
For lovers caught in eternal time,
who can break the spell of romance?
Bowing with my hands clasped, I give away my throne.
Lowering my head, devoted to the beauty by my side.
The wheel of fate turns, granting blessings or misfortune.
Will it be destiny’s trial or reward?
Heaven’s will cannot be known,
weaving together weals and woes.
For lovers caught in eternal time,
who can break the spell of romance?
Who can break the spell of romance?
Translators: The Magpie Bridge Brigade 鹊桥小队翻译组
https://magpiebridgebrigade.cn
Twitter/FB/IG @BrigadeMagpie 公众号/微博: 鹊桥小队翻译组
Please offer incense, Your Majesty.
Consort Estime, Consort Astuce,
Concubine An and Concubine Délice, please offer incense.
Noble Lady Vertu and Noble Lady Joie,
please offer incense.
How dare you! Hiding here sneakily!
This humble concubine bows in respect
before Your Majesty and My Ladies.
My precious Buddha! I thought it was somebody else.
I didn't expect it to be
Your Highness Concubine Sourire.
Oh, you are not Concubine Sourire anymore.
What should I call you?
This humble concubine is Mochou of
the Temple of Pure Dew.
Mochou is your name.
But why do you address yourself as
"humble concubine" rather than "humble nun"?
Are you resigned to your lowly position
but refusing to obey the Budhha?
Mistress Mochou is observing Buddhist
practice without her head shaved.
She is not a real nun.
Lady Vertu is so concerned about Mochou.
You care about Mochou the most after all.
It was careless of Concubine Délice
to step on Mochou's hand just now.
I wonder if it needs urgent attention.
She's fine, she's fine.
Mochou does a lot of tough manual labor.
Stepping on her hands is
nothing to worry about.
Tough manual labor?
Yes.
After all, she is no longer an exalted concubine.
She has to chop firewood, wash and
starch clothes, and clean the floor.
She's no different than the new nuns here.
But Mochou is an esteemed person from the palace.
This must be hard for her.
Her treatment here is only natural.
Once you've entered the land of Buddhism,
you must leave behind material
possessions and earthly cares.
Buddhism teaches us that every life
is created equal.
There shouldn't be an exception for Mochou.
I agree, Your Majesty.
Your Majesty,
Mochou practices Buddhism here
on His Majesty's orders.
Moreover, she is the mother of a princess.
Just looking at her pale face,
you can see how frail she is.
But the nuns are still making her do
all these onerous tasks.
Isn't that being too harsh?
As Her Majesty said,
the past is renounced upon stepping
into the Gate of Emptiness.
The princess is the princess
and Mochou is Mochou.
His Majesty also said,
Consort Estime is the only mother of the princess.
You mustn't distort His Majesty's
edict, Lady Vertu.
Huan'er, the floor is cold.
You don't need to kneel.
Lady Vertu, come back here.
You shouldn't inhabit the space Mochou is in.
Go. I'm all right.
Different people have their own place.
People and spirits cannot walk the same path.
Concubines and commoners
cannot stand side by side.
Your Majesty, although Mochou
has left the palace,
she doesn't deserve physical and verbal abuse.
Buddhism emphasizes having a peaceful mind.
Lady Vertu, your impetuous behavior is improper.
You cannot worship the Buddha today.
Kneel here and reflect on your actions.
The main prayer hall is in the back.
Your Majesty, this way, please.
My Ladies, please.
Mind the threshold when you exit.
Please.
Your Majesty must be tired after a long day.
Would you like to rest now?
Concubine An has perceptive eyes.
Can't you see Her Majesty is truly pleased today?
I was not pleased, but reassured.
It's reassuring to know that Zhen Huan
will no longer be a threat.
Had I not seen it myself,
I never would have known that she's
been living like a cockroach.
A life like this will wear down
her resolve more than death.
So this is what it means to
"live a life worse than death".
Today, when I left ‌the‌ ‌Temple‌ ‌of‌ ‌Pure‌ ‌Dew,
I told Prioress Jingbai not to treat
Zhen Huan with any generosity.
Just let her life take its course.
Although Zhen Huan is no threat to us,
His Majesty hasn't completely gotten over her.
You two should put more effort
into gaining His Majesty's favor.
Yes, Your Majesty.
Does Your Majesty feel better now?
Don't worry, I'm used to being unwell at this age.
Your Majesty has been coughing a lot.
I will tell the kitchen to make some
sugared loquat soup to soothe your throat.
You smell strongly of medicinal oil today.
It's making me a little dizzy.
I must have used too much on my knees.
They were aching badly from kneeling.
That was a punishment.
The Empress wanted to make an
example of you to others in the harem.
I misspoke and deserved the punishment.
But Concubine Sourire ...
Mochou... has suffered immensely.
I cannot put my mind at peace.
What do you want to tell me? Be direct.
I implore Your Majesty to shield
Mochou from endless hardship,
on account of her being
Princess Longyue's birth mother.
Why are you so faithful to Mochou?
We are...
friends of unwavering faith.
I heard about what happened today.
The Empress and Concubine Délice
were somewhat out of line.
But not seriously so.
I can't help feeling sorry for Princess Longyue.
She was separated from her birth mother at birth.
If Mochou suffers torment
at the Temple of Pure Dew,
that would be even more reason to pity Princess Longyue.
It is right to not take things to extremes.
All right. I will send someone to see her.
I can at least prevent Mochou
from being tortured to death.
I thank Your Majesty.
Hearing Your Majesty say so,
I could die now without regrets.
You always care about others,
but what about yourself?
Concubine An and Concubine Délice
are vying for the Emperor's favor.
How long has it been
since you last saw the Emperor?
His Majesty will summon me
when he is in the mood.
Your Majesty, I have another favor to ask of you.
Now that the Palace of Pearl Jade is unoccupied,
I wonder if it could be granted to me.
You intend to look after the palace
for Concubine Sourire?
Since Concubine Sourire left the palace,
everyone has been saying that the
Palace of Pearl Jade is inauspicious.
I have been living with Consort Estime.
While that makes it convenient to
take care of Princess Longyue,
I always feel that the palace
is not spacious enough.
I've been thinking…
Instead of moving elsewhere
when the princess is older,
why not allow me to move to
the Palace of Pearl Jade now?
Have you thought about it carefully?
If Concubine Sourire is still
an untied knot in the Emperor's heart,
once you move in,
it will be just like living in the Cold Palace.
Once his Majesty unties the knot,
everything will be fine.
That's by no means certain.
But if you wish to, I will allow it.
I thank Your Majesty.
Ajin.
It's been a while, Jade.
Despite the poor fare in the temple,
you're looking prettier than ever!
And you're even more smarmy and annoying.
Your Lordship said that you would come
five days before Longyue’s birthday.
But you didn't say exactly what time.
So I came early.
I didn't expect that Your Lordship
would come even earlier.
I had my own reasons for wanting to wait here.
If we were to chance upon each other,
that would be a pleasant surprise indeed.
If we were to come across one another
without prior arrangement,
wouldn't that be an arrangement of fate?
To be honest, when it comes to love
and affection,
I don’t believe in fate.
People often use “deeply shared fate”
as an excuse to get close to someone.
And “we are not fated” as a pretense
to end an attachment.
I always find your remarks
strangely insightful.
You draw a conclusion that leads to a new idea.
Your Lordship flatters me.
Maybe one day if I had nowhere to go
and no future,
then I would agree it must have been fated.
Not believing in fate would not be surprising
when you were in your prime.
But now that you live by Buddha's side,
don't you believe in fate?
I am living in a temple
but I also hold on to some beliefs of my own.
Buddhism is so profound
and I've never understood it entirely.
I just hope that Buddha's all-embracing teachings
can bring peace into people's hearts.
As for fate,
I always feel that things are more
determined by people's actions.
There is no need to use the word “fate”
to explain encounters and partings.
Madam Orchid, what brings you here?
Mistress.
Sit down, Mistress.
You see, this is a postnatal formula prescribed by Dr. Wen.
Lady Vertu asked me to bring it to you.
The medicine has been measured,
so you can take it accordingly.
And these clothes
are from Consort Estime,
to provide you additional changes of clothes.
Is Meizhuang well? And Longyue?
They are both well. It's just….
you ask only about them.
Aren't you going to ask about
Her Majesty the Empress Dowager?
Meizhuang relies on Her Majesty's
graces in the palace.
If Meizhuang is well,
then Her Majesty must be well too.
What about His Majesty,
don't you care about him anymore?
If there was national mourning,
all under Heaven would be notified.
So I wouldn't need to hear it from you.
Mistress, you misspoke.
Mistress, pardon me for saying this.
Your inability to let go of your resentments
is causing yourself more suffering.
This is the ejiao granted by the Empress Dowager.
It's good for replenishing qi and regulating circulation.
Her Majesty hopes it will help
calm your qi and your mind.
I am guilty of my offences.
I thank Her Majesty for still having pity on me.
Mistress, you are intelligent.
You understand although
Her Majesty is ailed by sickness,
her mind is still clear.
But in some matters,
Her Majesty cannot intervene
even if she understands.
Mistress, since you are now living in the temple,
why don't you copy some sutras
to pray for Her Majesty?
I will come here once a month to retrieve them.
Her Majesty said that the sutras will
only be effective if copied by you.
Please thank Her Majesty profusely for me.
I will put forth my best effort to copy the sutras
and pray for Heaven's blessings
on Her Majesty.
Princess Longyue is turning one soon.
Although there won't be a large banquet,
the palace still regards it an important event.
The princess must have
received many valuable gifts.
That's wonderful.
A princess living without her
birth mother is usually less favored.
Although Princess Wenyi is
fostered by Consort Honnête,
His Majesty still adores Princess Longyue more.
A prince can rely on his own strength
to strive for a higher status,
but the future of a princess
relies solely upon her imperial father's favor.
Do you know who is currently looking after
the Empress Première's belongings?
Empress Première's favorite clothing
and accessories are kept by His Majesty.
The rest is kept by the Empress.
The Empress Dowager also has some.
Did Empress Première have ...
any favorite accessory such as a choker?
Empress Première had a hibiscus choker
made of suet white jade.
It was her favorite.
I believe it was a gift presented by
His Majesty on their grand wedding.
Can regular white jade be used to
create a similar choker?
That wouldn't be difficult.
Jinxi, retrieve my jewelry box.
Longyue is my only daughter.
As her birth mother,
I wish I could show how much I care for her.
Madam Orchid, please take all my jewelry
and ask the craftsmen at the Household Department
to craft a choker similar to what you described.
If Longyue can wear it on her birthday,
it could be a token of my love for her.
Mistress, you don't have a lot of savings.
Besides, it doesn't cost
this much to hire a craftsman.
This bracelet is enough.
Don't worry, Mistress.
I will do my utmost.
Thank you, Madam Orchid.
Mistress, it's cold outside. Please return.
I will come retrieve the sutras monthly
as the Empress Dowager requested.
I hope you will be conscientious about copying the sutras for Her Majesty.
I will obey Her Majesty's command.
She's coming. Hurry, let's move.
My Lady, why didn't you ask
Madam Orchid to bring you justice?
Or ask her to tell Madam Abbess.
Madam Abbess is kind but unassertive.
Her words carry less weight than Prioress Jingbai's.
After leaving the palace,
those who wanted me dead then
aren't just going to let me live in peace now.
The more hardship I have now,
the more at ease their hearts will be.
That way, they will care less about my Longyue.
This is all I can do for my daughter.
By having you copy the sutras,
Her Majesty is protecting you
from being harmed by them.
Endless Longing is broken.
The zither itself is fine,
but the string has snapped.
“Few understand my melody. Who would
be listening now that I broke my lute string?”
[Manifold Little Hills by Yue Fei]
The string of Endless Longing snapped.
There is no need to long for anyone.
So pretty.
Just look at our Longyue.
She has been a natural beauty from birth.
She certainly has.
Just look at how intricate her clothing is.
All right, that's all right.
His Majesty the Emperor.
Peace to Your Majesty.
Rise.
I thank Your Majesty.
I haven't come for a few days.
Longyue won't even smile at me now.
Your Majesty, that's not true.
Longyue is so little.
She will smile once Your Majesty holds her.
Here, I'll hold her.
Yes, Your Majesty.
Let me see if Longyue has grown heavier.
Where did this choker come from?
When I was preparing Longyue's accessories a few days ago,
I realized she was missing a jade choker.
So I had the Household Department make one.
Does Your Majesty not like it?
No, it's pretty. But it looks familiar somehow.
I remember Empress Première had a choker similar to this one.
But Consort Estime married in late
and never had a chance to see it.
The craftsmanship of the Household Department is largely the same.
But this choker is not as finely made
as Empress Première's.
- Su Peisheng.
- Your Majesty.
Go retrieve Empress Première's choker
and give it to the princess.
Yes, Your Majesty.
I thank Your Majesty on behalf of the princess.
All right, the banquet is about to start.
Let's all go get seated.
Longyue must be hungry now.
Come here, Longyue. Let's go.
You're hungry, aren't you?
- Let's go.
- Yes, let's go.
Anqi Temple
[Taoist Temple of Peaceful Dwelling]
Translators: The Magpie Bridge Brigade 鹊桥小队翻译组
Twitter/FB/IG @BrigadeMagpie 公众号/微博: 鹊桥小队翻译组
I've been working in the harsh sun.
Please forgive my intruding to ask for some water.
Nebular, go get some tea.
Yes.
Please, come in.
This way.
Thank you so much.
How may I address you?
You can call me Serene.
You must be living in the Temple of Pure Dew.
I am.
I haven't gathered enough firewood.
I'll go back later.
Your Venerable Highness, the tea is ready.
Good. Please serve it.
Are you ... Consort Dowager Serein？
You know my title?
Yes, I should call you Venerable Abbess Serene.
Are you from the palace?
I heard a Mistress Zhen from the
palace lives in the Temple of Pure Dew.
It must be you.
Pardon me for my blunt eyes.
Please.
This is my personal maid, Nebular.
It is serendipitous to meet you today.
Ever since I left the palace upon
the prior emperor's passing,
I haven't met anyone from the palace.
It would seem my fate with Your Venerable
Highness is greater than with others.
Aside from the fact that we met today,
I also have Endless Longing, the zither, with me.
It must have been cherished by
Your Venerable Highness.
Really?
It's in the Temple of Pure Dew now.
When I left the palace,
I left behind both Endless Longing,
the zither, and Eternal Promise, the flute.
Because they were of no use to me
after the prior emperor passed away.
I never would have expected the zither to be in your possession.
It has been many years since I parted with it.
If you wouldn't mind,
could you bring it and allow me to take a look at it?
I would have liked to, Your Venerable Highness.
But a few days ago, I accidentally broke a string.
If you don't mind,
you can bring it to me.
I will try my best and might be able to fix it.
It would bring peace to my mind if it were
back in Your Venerable Highness's possession.
If it can not be repaired,
then we need only lament the loss of
Endless Longing's sublime sounds.
Please come visit again
and bring Endless Longing with you.
I like speaking with you.
Your Venerable Highness is so generous.
How could I refuse?
Please.
Your Majesty,
the princess turned one today.
Your Majesty drank quite a lot.
Let's hurry and have you rest.
Otherwise, Your Majesty will feel uncomfortable from the drinking.
My head feels a little dizzy. Let's go back.
Concubine An wanted to accompany Your Majesty,
but you refused Her Highness.
Allow me to accompany Your Majesty
back to the Hall of Mental Cultivation.
It's the Palace of Pearl Jade.
Who is that at the entrance?
Your Majesty, that is the Fourth Prince.
Why did Hongli come to the palace?
All the princes and princesses have come
to celebrate Princess Longyue's birthday.
Except for the Fifth Prince, who caught a cold.
Tell Hongli to stay in the Summer Palace.
And not hang around in the palace.
Yes.
I bow before Imperial Father.
What are you doing here?
Her Highness Sourire ...
She treated me very well.
She...
I understand that Her Highness
angered you, Imperial Father.
Please forgive me.
How did she treat you well?
Her Highness taught me to read.
She knew that I missed you,
and that I was afraid of disturbing you.
So she told me to pay respects
to you from a distance.
You wanted to see me?
Yes.
Go back and see to your books.
I will call for you when I'm available.
Yes.
Thank you, Father. I bid you goodbye.
Your Majesty, the Palace of Pearl Jade
has been assigned to Lady Vertu.
Lady Vertu?
The Empress Dowager granted it to Lady Vertu.
She will be moving in a couple days.
I will take a look inside then.
Yes.
Lower the sedan.
This place has been untouched since Zhen left.
Yes.
Lady Vertu also requested that
nothing should be changed.
This was her favorite, the rose hairpin.
The jade shoes I gifted her...
She did not bring either.
She took nothing.
She left swiftly without any attachments.
Your Majesty, she took Endless Longing,
the zither that you granted.
Endless Longing.
Here we are.
Be careful.
Mother, look.
Your Lordship.
Speaking of the devil.
I should stop talking about
people behind their back.
He just arrived from the north,
and came here even before his estate.
You came at the perfect time.
The weather is nice today,
so I brought Endless Longing
for Your Venerable Highness.
This was my own mistake, but I'm relying
on Your Venerable Highness's help now.
This is my personal maid, Jade.
I brought her here to pay our respects.
Peace to Your Venerable Highness and Your lordship
Jade rarely bows to me formally.
I guess I'm benefiting from you being here.
You have pretty eyes.
And your skin is fair and delicate.
Looking at your eyes,
they resemble your Mistress's.
I hadn't noticed that before.
Now you mention it, I do think
you two look like sisters.
We grew up together.
We are as close as sisters.
Now that my parents have been banished to Ninguta,
she has gone through a lot of
hardship because of my status.
Everyone in this world suffers hardship.
I liked her at first sight, just as I did with you.
I don't want the rest of her life
to be ruined because of me.
If there's an appropriate match,
I hope Your Venerable Highness and Your Lordship
could help to betroth her to a good family.
That would also fulfill a cherished desire of mine.
My Lady, why would you say that?
Do you resent me and want to send me away?
Your Mistress is planning ahead for you.
Yunli, I'm entrusting this matter to you.
You must find a good match for Jade.
Mother, please be assured. I will keep it in mind.
I just heard from Her Venerable Highness that
Your Lordship was visiting the far north
for the past few months.
His Majesty sent me on a whim,
to inspect the officials in the north
under the disguise of plain clothes.
I left in such a hurry that
I wasn't able to bid you farewell.
It's been nearly three months since we last met.
Yes, it has been eighty-seven days.
Your Lordship has a good memory.
Your Lordship is well-learned.
The trip was long, but quite fruitful.
I took the opportunity to detour by Ningguta.
This letter is for you.
From my father?
Yes.
Huan'er, your mother and I are doing well.
No need to worry about us.
I learned that you and Jade are practicing
Buddhism in the Temple of Pure Dew.
This is also good.
The pieces are already in place.
Don't make any futile efforts.
Let us all take care of ourselves
at each end of this earth.
Don't miss us too much.
It can be seen from the letter that
Uncle Zhen is healthy since
his writing is vigorous and forceful.
He also said he is living a more peaceful life
away from the quarrels of the imperial court.
Ningguta is harsh and bleak all year round.
My parents are advanced in years.
How can I rest assured?
Although Ninguta is bleak and harsh,
it offers a time of solitude.
When I visited Uncle Zhen,
I could sense from his words that
he was at peace with his predicament.
The imperial court might look grand and glorious,
but it's full of conflicts and fights.
At an advanced age,
Uncle Zhen can find satisfaction in a peaceful place.
"With the flames of war unending for three months,
a letter from home is worth ten thousand pieces of gold."
I thank Your Lordship.
You are my confidant.
You need not stand on ceremony.
My mother mentioned Jade's marriage earlier.
I have someone in mind.
I would like to know your thoughts on it.
- Ajin.
- What?
He's grown up with me since childhood.
So I can vouch for his character.
Moreover, he and Jade
are already somewhat familiar.
So it's not a blind marriage.
Well, if Your Lordship says so.
Your Lordship,
I won't agree even if Ajin does.
My Lady is to practice Buddhism in the
temple for the rest of her life.
She will only have Jinxi if I leave her.
I regard My Lady as my elder sister.
How could I have the heart to live
comfortably while she is left to suffer?
Jade,
if you marry Ajin, you can live
in the Cooling Terrace.
You can still see her frequently.
You can also invite her to stay
with you from time to time.
Is Your Lordship's intention to marry me to Ajin
so that My Lady will stay at the Cooling Terrace?
Are you trying to help me
and My Lady to see each other,
or helping yourself to see My Lady?
Your Lordship might as well make that clear.
Jade!
Jade,
are you trying to help Huan'er,
or upset her?
My Lady.
Your Lordship misspoke my name.
My monastic name is Mochou.
It wouldn't be good to make a hasty
decision about Jade's marriage.
We shall give the matter further thought.
That won't be necessary.
Whether it's a quick decision or carefully thought out,
I won't marry someone I don't have feelings for.
But if it's someone I love,
I wouldn't have any regrets even if I were only to
become his secondary wife.
But in the current situation,
I just want to be with My Lady.
I don't deserve Jade after all.
Jade has her temperament and aspirations.
Having been through my family's
misfortunes together,
she has stopped caring about many things.
I hope Your Lordship can forgive her.
I acted rashly today.
I will talk to her about it after we get back.
Feeling better?
Yes.
I know that His Lordship was acting for my benefit.
I'm just your maid in his eyes.
So naturally,
I can only marry his attendant.
Jade,
you have a sharp mind.
But don't chase a dead end.
Although His Lordship
doesn't know you are my sister,
he knows we have a sisterly bond.
He wouldn't hastily betroth you to his attendant.
It is because he cares about you
that he wants you to be married
to someone he trusts.
You and Ajin have always gotten along well.
No wonder His Lordship had that idea.
But ...
You and His Lordship get along well too.
So you suspect that His Lordship is trying
to get close to me using your marriage?
I just think His Lordship treats you too kindly.
He even traveled thousands of miles to
bring you a letter from our family.
How does Wen Shichu treat me,
and I him?
Dr. Wen always treats you well
and you never overstep the bounds of propriety.
Actually, since we came to the Temple of Pure Dew,
I've been thinking that you should
find someone to rely on for life.
Of course,
His Lordship surpasses Dr. Wen in his
character, appearance, demeanor, and erudition.
But His Lordship is the younger brother of His Majesty.
You think I don't know that he's
His Majesty's younger brother?
Besides, I don't have feelings for him.
I know what I said earlier upsets you.
But even if you don't have feelings for His Lordship,
does he not have feelings for you?
There are some things
that we need to be aware of in advance.
We can’t afford any more trouble, can we?
His Lordship sees me as his confidant,
and I view him the same way.
I will certainly mind appropriate boundaries,
and avoid bringing disaster upon myself.
I’ve been restless ever since summer began.
Soon it will be another autumn.
It feels as though I'll have to go through
what happened to Huan'er all over again.
I could do nothing but witness her suffering.
It was like that then and it will be now, and always.
All is well with Huan'er.
Please be at ease, My Lady.
You’re always telling me she’s fine.
I know that’s not really the truth.
You're just trying to comfort me.
I also know that
You would be even sadder than I am
if you were to see her living unhappily.
Living alone in the Palace of Pearl Jade,
you also suffer from worrying
about her day and night, My Lady.
I might be living alone.
But with you frequently coming
to care for my health,
it's hardly as though I'm living in the Cold Palace.
My Lady,
you didn’t have to move into the Palace of Pearl Jade.
Since you moved here,
His Majesty hasn't called for you.
Why are you putting yourself through this?
As long as His Majesty can't get over
the block in his heart
he won't be able to step into the Palace of Pearl Jade.
You know why I am doing this.
Yesterday Lunar came to tell me that
you cough frequently, My Lady.
So I stewed loquat with rock sugar.
Please have some.
Even if it can heal sickness, it can't heal the heart.
I shall take my leave.
- Mistress.
- Ajin.
Today is the Dragon Boat Festival.
His Lordship is at the imperial banquet.
He asked me to send you some
sweet rice dumplings for the festival.
Thank you for thinking of us.
His Lordship said that he's been busy
at the palace for the past few days,
and that he will visit you when he has time.
His Lordship is often busy.
It's only natural that he's not able to visit.
It's not that His Lordship is busy himself,
but that the Empress Dowager is trying
to arrange a marriage for him.
Really?
Of course.
Otherwise, why would His Lordship be unhappy?
Her Majesty has been urging him all these years,
saying, "how could a lord not have a wife at this age,"
not even a concubine?"
This time Her Majesty has set him up
with the daughter of Duke of Pei,
called Meng Jingxian or something.
That’s good news.
At His Lordship’s age,
many others are already crowded with children.
It’s time to have a wife to
take charge of domestic affairs.
But His Lordship is reluctant to marry.
I thought that since His Lordship
regarded you as his confidant, Mistress,
you must understand his heart too.
I didn't expect
that you would feel happy for him.
I don't want to hear that. I'll take my leave.
Translators: The Magpie Bridge Brigade 鹊桥小队翻译组
https://magpiebridgebrigade.cn
Twitter/FB/IG @BrigadeMagpie 公众号/微博: 鹊桥小队翻译组
Theme: The Phoenix Taking Flight
[phoenix is the symbol of an empress]
The dreams I dimly recall;
The past I hardly remember,
amidst the autumn moons and the spring flowers.
Like the moon's reflection on water
or flowers seen through mist - floating and drifting.
The joyous sounds you brought;
The silence you left;
Changing faster than clouds can turn to rain.
Our minds resonated;
Our hearts beat in unison;
But we lost what we once possessed.
A poem to converse;
A melody to accompany;
A heart to bind to mine.
I hoped for endless longing and eternal promise,
but I’m left with only the flute and the zither.
With affection, I pleased;
With my heart, I committed;
With my arms, I embraced.
I desired to be remembered;
Desired to be cherished;
Why am I only hated and deceived?
My wish ran against my will.
Behold the mockery of destiny and the game of fate.
My unwavering love is gone
like flowers swept away in the wind.
Praying for a bright moon;
Praying for a rising sun;
Dreaming to bask in the spring breezes.
But the unsparing northern winds carry snow and rain
to destroy the aspirations of the plum tree.
A phoenix about to take flight rustles its wings
but the arc of its flight is unseen.
The phoenix tree sways in the wind,
shedding memories in the whispers of the falling leaves.